Hy Rosen Cartoons
Hy Rosen Cartoons
1964-1971
Rosen, Hy.
4.1 linear ft.
180 original editorial cartoons (1965-1967) and 39 proofs (1964, circa 1970-1971).
149552
Biographical History
Hy Rosen (1923-2011) was an American editorial cartoonist and sculptor.
Born on February 10, 1923 to Russian immigrants, Hyman Joseph Rosen was an Albany native who studied at the Art Students League in New York City as well as the Chicago Art Institute. In 1945, after service in World War II, Mr. Rosen sought a job with the Albany Times-Union as a photographer (a job he held while in the military) but ended up as the paper's editorial cartoonist, a position he held for more than forty years. During his tenure at the Times Union Rosen fought for cartoonists to have increased creative control over their work. Some of his cartoons appeared under the title "As Hy Rosen Sees It" and these cartoons were syndicated nationally. Rosen retired from the Times Union in 1989 and during the early 1990s his cartoons continued to occasionally appear on Sundays. During this time he also drew a weekly cartoon for the Albany news for WNYT.
He won many awards for his cartooning work, including the Fourth Estate Award from the American Legion in 1980 and three awards from the Freedoms Foundation. In 1966 Rosen was a journalism fellow at Stanford. Two compilations of Rosen cartoons have been published: As Hy Rosen saw it: a collection of penetrating cartoon commentaries as they appeared in the Times Union (1970) and Do they tell you what to draw?: a decade of political cartoons (1980). They have also been included in Best Editorial Cartoons of the Year and From Rocky to Pataki: character and caricatures in New York politics (1998). Rosen was a member of the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists (AAEC) since its founding in 1957 and served as its president in 1972.
In addition to cartooning, Rosen was an accomplished sculptor working in ceramic and bronze. From 1968 to 1970, Rosen studied sculpture at the State University of New York-Albany. The New York State Police Academy and the New York State Museum are among the organizations that have commissioned works by Rosen and his women veterans memorial can be seen at the Empire State Legislative Plaza in Albany.
Hy Rosen died in February 2011.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hy Rosen Cartoons consist of 2 series: Cartoons- original artwork and Cartoons- proofs. Cartoons- original artwork contains 180 editorial cartoons drawn by Rosen for the Albany Times-Union from 1965 to 1967. In the corner of some of Rosen's cartoons appears a small figure that acts as a commentator on the events depicted in the cartoon. Although working for a paper in the North, of particular interest are Rosen's cartoons relating to the civil rights movement. Rosen commented on civil rights related murders in the South as well as the connection between activists from the Northeast and events in the South. Also of interest are Rosen's caricatures of dysfunctional New York state government and ousted U.S. Congressman Adam Clayton Powell Jr. of Harlem.
The majority of the cartoons are dated. Rosen worked primarily in brusk and ink and pen and ink on illustration board with some pencil and screening. Notations appear in the borders. The original artwork varies in size, but earlier cartoons are generally 14 1/4" x 20 1/4" while the last year of cartoons are generally 11 1/2" x 13 1/2".
Cartoons- proofs is comprised of 39 proofs of cartoons drawn by Rosen. At the top of most is the title, "As Hy Rosen Sees It". The majority of the proofs are undated but are from approximately 1970-1971. However, 4 proofs bear dates from 1964.
Arrangement of the Collection
The cartoons and are arranged chronologically with undated items appearing at the end of the series.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Art -- Sculptors; New York State; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Rosen, Hy.; Times-Union (Albany, N.Y.); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- New York (State); Cartoonists -- United States.; Civil rights movements -- United States -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Editorial cartoons -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Strikes and lockouts -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Proofs (printed matter); Cartoonists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Hy Rosen, 1967 and 1971.
Inventory
- Cartoons- original artwork
  - 1965 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
    Feb 26: "Clean as Mississippi mud!"
    Apr 23: There's a sucker born every minute, man!"
    May 5: "...And what's more she is prejudiced!"
    Aug 26: "Got me another man of the cloth!"
    Oct 1: "I swear to God she was coming at me with a knife!"
    Oct 13: "Sorry...no room!"
    Oct 17: "Agony and the ecstasy"
    Dec 2: "C'est moi, le super homme!"
  - 1966 Jan - Mar (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    Jan 26: "We've got them cornered!"
    Feb 16: "Welcome to Socialist Realism!"
    Feb 24: "...Except when you have to bail us out!"
    Mar 16: "Don't give me that no, no, no business!"
    Mar 30: "Yes, Mr. President, mine are identifiable!"
  - 1966 Apr - May (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    Apr 10: The lonliest guy in the world
    Apr 15: Now he tells us!"
    Apr 24: Cubesville
    May 4: Chinese puzzle
    May 6: "Filthy pictures?"
    May 15: Bulletin: Red Chinese leader, Mao, makes first public appearance since Nov. 26
    May 16: "Would you believe...half past next year?"
  - 1966 Jun (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
    Jun 3: "Nice to have a soft landing!"
    Jun 16: Nothing scared
    Jun 17: "Show me the way to go home..."
    Jun 19: "I trust you enjoyed the sermon!"
    Jun 20: "They're conducting a teach-in at the university!"
    Jun 21: Apartheid
    Jun 22: "For our final act..."
    Jun 23: Closing in...
    Jun 24: Faisal's two way salute
    Jun 26: "No charge for alternations!"
    Jun 27: "Like they say in the trade, 'fasten your seat belt!'"
    Jun 28: Heat or light?
    Jun 29: The moment of truth
  - 1966 Jul (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
    Jul 1: "Cheer up, you're just in time for Medicare!"
    Jul 1: Target
    Jul 7: "Man, that's progress!"
    Jul 8: "Will this be 'IN' in November?"
    Jul 10: "Geneva Convention...Who's she?"
    Jul 11: "...And I got the halo to prove it!"
    Jul 12: A Midsummer Night's dream
    Jul 13: "And you better believe it!"
    Jul 13: Track and field
    Jul 15: "Carry me back to old Virginy..."
    Jul 17: Rorschach test
    Jul 18: Front line, U.S.A.
    Jul 26: "Help!"
    Jul 27: "Now, if he'd show a humanitarian policy in this direction!"
    Jul 28: "I've worked too hard...you try broom power!"
    Jul 31: "I understand you've been known to have a drop..."
  - 1966 Aug 2-15 (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
    Aug 2: "They just told us where to go!"
    Aug 3: "The boy was only making use of his constitutional rights!"
    Aug 4: The great 'lip' forward
    Aug 6: "Just eloped!"
    Aug 7: "Hush, now, we haven't lost a daughter, we've gained a Democrat!"
    Aug 9: "It will never fly!"
    Aug 10: "We try to run a respectable house!"
    Aug 11: "I'll huff and I'll puff and I'll blow your open housing down!"
    Aug 12: "No, no, the idea is to get him to push you in!"
    Aug 15: "Due to minor difficulties..."
  - 1966 Aug 18-31 (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
    Aug 18: But no brain power
    Aug 19: "Fly now, pay later"
    Aug 22: "The tighter he gets...the bigger his hangover!"
    Aug 23: "And it makes you feel like a mini!"
    Aug 24: "Yeah, yeah, yeah...."
    Aug 25: The fountain of youth
    Aug 26: "My friends...?"
    Aug 28: "What's a mother to do?"
    Aug 30: "Give 'em hell, Harry!"
    Aug 31: Platform
  - 1966 Sep (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
    Sep 1: "War is hell!"
    Sep 2: "Now there is 1-A material!"
    Sep 4: "It isn't your shoes I'm worried about filling, it's the big hole!"
    Sep 5: "Now that the new minimum is $1.60, do you think..."
    Sep 8: For better or for worse
    Sep 8: "What's in a name?--Eh Franklin--I mean Frank"
    Sep 11: Long distance stroke
    Sep 12: "Man I just want to cool it!"
    Sep 13: The right to vote
    Sep 14: Walk through space
  - 1966 Dec (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
    Dec 15: "Copy"
    Dec 16: Legacy
    Dec 18: "We cannot escape history"....Lincoln"
    Dec 19: "Critics to the left of me, critics to the right of me. Now I know how Gen. Custer felt!"
    Dec 20: "It's aimed at the U.S.A. by way of Peking!"
    Dec 21: "The bigger they are... the harder they fall!"
    Dec 22: "God Bless Us Everyone!" said tiny U Thant, the last of all
    Dec 23: "Look...it's possible!"
    Dec 25: "Yes, Sgt. Campos you belong to us all"
    Dec 26: "Like I said, let 100 flowers bloom"
    Dec 27: "He ain't heavy mister he's my brother!"
    Dec 28: "It's only when the going has been rough..."
    Dec 29: "I beg your pardon...happy...what?"
  - 1967 Jan (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
    Jan 1: "Do not forsake me, oh, my darlin'..."
    Jan 17: Desert Rat
    Jan 18: "Like some guy said..."We'll bury you!">
    Jan 19: "Who knows some good may come of it!">
    Jan 20: Confucius say: Mao got wrong slant!
    Jan 22: "What's it mean...he's reading humpty dumpty?"
    Jan 26: Air pollution
    Jan 29: "Let's face it. Yeuuuck!
    Jan 31: Booster
  - 1967 Feb (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
    Feb 1: "Welcome to Interstate pig-sty!"
    Feb 2: "Keep the faith, baby!"
    Feb 3: "It looks like a long hard winter..."
    Feb 5: "They're breaking up, that old gang of mine!">
    Feb 6: "Gummy is a watchdog that will lick 'em!"
    Feb 8: No place to build a nest
    Feb 9: "It's his new record 'keep the mouth shut baby!"
    Feb 12: "P-s-s-s-t.. J. Edgar Hoover sent me!"
    Feb 14: The year of the goat
    Feb 15: "I'm here to protect you from the criminals!"
    Feb 16: "Are there any funds available for Sat. night dates?"
    Feb 19: "And please make everybody work together so that our neighborhood will be safe!"
    Feb 21: "It's a rough neighborhood!"
    Feb 22: "Scab!"
    Feb 23: "Keep the faith, baby!"
    Feb 26: Morality- Feb 1967
    Feb 28 "Sacred cow!"
  - 1967 Mar (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
    Mar 2: Meridan Revisited
    Mar 5: "Now... keep your eye on the bunny!"
    Mar 7: "Now I know why they cal it selective service act!"
    Mar 8: "I shall return!"
    Mar 12: "Thanks!"
    Mar 14: "Let them eat crow!"
    Mar 16: "Gentlemen, this isn't a penny ante riverboat game!"
    Mar 19: "Hey boss, hold my end while I take care of some business!"
    Mar 22: "Hoy..need a new image?"
    Mar 26: "I sure would like to build 'em a new home!"
    Mar 29: "You can play on my team anytime!"
  - 1967 Apr (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
    Apr 2: The not so white knight
    Apr 5: "Goodnight Chet...Chet...Chet...this is a recording"
    Apr 6: "Don't you know there is a constitutional convention here"
    Apr 7: "Who's the law around here?"
    Apr 9: "P-S-S-s-T you're off target!"
    Apr 12: "Don't give me that manana routine!"
    Apr 13: "And send us more light than heat!"
    Apr 14: "The score is powell 9, opponents 1!"
    Apr 16: "It's a new ball of wax!"Apr 13:
    Apr 17: "Good night Jack, good night Storrs"
    Apr 19: "Man, you turn me on!"
    Apr 20: untitled
    Apr 21: "He's getting a lot of mileage for a slow poke!"
    Apr 23: Never underestimate the power of a woman
    Apr 25: Rendezvous
    Apr 26: Death Row Reprieve
    Apr 27: "Welcome to Washington combat zone!"
    Apr 28: "I think it's a Greek tragedy!"
    Apr 30: The new champion
  - 1967 May (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
    May 1: "It's our new leader and the face is familiar!"
    May 2: "Let my people go!"
    May 3: The master of suspense at work
    May 4: Splashdown
    May 5: "Right in the schoolhouse door- where have I seen that?
    May 7: "To the guillotine!"
    May 9: Terminal
    May 16: "Learn, baby, learn!"
    May 17: "He's gone 'hippie' on us!"
    May 18: Gun boat diplomacy
    May 26: Souvenir
    May 28: "Yes, it stands for and on something!"
    May 30: Guardians of liberty
  - 1967 Jun (Oversize 3, Folder 6)
    Jun 13: "Was that trip necessary?"
    Jun 14: New battlefield
    Jun 15: "It's your honor!"
    Jun 16: "What in Dodd's name are you doing out there?"
    Jun 18: "My technique is the soft shoe!"
    Jun 20: "Another 'peace loving' delegate heard from!"
    Jun 22: "Nothing like a little oil to make it slide"
    Jun 23: "Anyone call for a wiseman?"
    Jun 25: "Yes sir...8 lbs. 10 ozs. and his future is up to us!"
    Jun 28: "...and then there is Hanoibush!"
  - 1967 Jul (Oversize 3, Folder 7)
    Jul 13: untitled (dancer held on top of a man's hand)
    Jul 30: Mid-Summer in Capitaland's Music
  - circa 1967-1968 (Oversize 3, Folder 8)
    Vintage '66
    "Funny how that number keeps coming up!"
    "Are you ready to test drive a '68 vote getter?"
    Spirit of '67
    "Imagine, t he nut wants Arabs to sit down and talk peace with Israel"
    It's that bloomin' time of the year
    [Lost soul, Lawn birds, lady from Broadway, Celebrity manager]
- Cartoons - proofs, Title listed at top: "As Hy Rosen See It"
  - 1964 (Box 1)
    Feb 23
    Apr 3
    May 15
    Jun 28
  - circa 1970-1971, 35 items (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
AFL-CIO B3F2
airline industry B1F5-B2F1
Alabama B1F1
American Federation of Television and Radio Artists B3F4
Argentina B1F4
armed forces B1F3 B2F4 B3F5
auto industry B1F4
Baker, Bobby B3F1
Biao, Lin B2F2 B2F4
Black Power B1F5 B2F2
Blaine Amendment B3F4
Brezhnev, Leonid Ilyich B1F4-B1F5 B2F4
Brinkley, David B3F4
brotherhood B1F1
Buddhists B1F4
budget B3F1
Canada B3F5
Carmichael, Stokely B1F5 B2F2
Central Intelligence Agency B3F2
China B1F3-B1F4 B2F4-B3F1 B3F5
civil rights B1F1 B1F4-B2F1 B3F3
college students B3F2 B3F5-B3F6
communism B3F2
Condon-Wadlin Law B3F2-B3F3
Congress B1F4-B2F1 B3F1 B3F4 B3F6
Congress of Racial Equality B1F5
corruption B3F3
cost of living B2F2
Cox, Harold B1F1
crime B1F5
de Gaulle, Charles B1F1-B1F4 B3F3 B3F5-B3F6
Democratic Party B2F3
desegregation B2F3
Dirksen, Everett B2F1 B3F1
Disney, Walt B2F4
Dodd, Thomas J. B1F4 B3F4 B3F6
draft B1F3 B3F3-B3F4
elections B1F3-B1F4 B2F2-B2F3
EXPO '67 B3F5
Faisal of Saudi Arabia B1F4
Fisher, Harold B3F3
France B1F3
free speech B2F2 B3F5
freedom B3F5
Fulbright, J. William B1F3-B1F4
Garrison, Jim B3F3
Geneva Convention B1F5
ghettos B2F3
Great Society B1F2 B2F4
Greece B3F4
gun control B2F1
gun lobby B2F1 B3F2
hate B1F1
Hershey, Lewis Blaine B3F3
Ho Chi Minh B1F2 B1F5 B2F3 B3F6
Hoffa, Jimmy B1F5
Hoover, J. Edgar B3F2
housing B2F1
Humphrey, Hubert B2F2
hunger B2F4 B3F5
Huntley, Chet B3F4
Illia, Arturo Umberto B1F4
India B2F4
inflation B1F2 B1F5 B2F3
Israel B3F6 B3F8
Javits, Jacob B3F8
Javits-Kuchel Bill B3F4
Jews B3F5
Johnson, Luci B. B2F1
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F2 B1F4-B3F4 B3F6
justice B1F1
Kennedy, Jacqueline B2F4
Kennedy, John F. B2F4 B3F3
Kennedy, Robert F. B1F4-B2F2 B2F4 B3F3 B3F8
King Jr., Martin Luther B3F4
Kosygin, Alexey B1F4-B1F5 B3F6
Ku Klux Klan B1F1
Ky, Nguyen Cao B1F2-B1F4
liberty B3F5
Lindsay, John B1F4
Liuzzo, Viola B1F1
LSD B1F3
Marshall, Thurgood B3F6
mass murder B1F5
McKissick, Fred B. B1F5
Meany, George B3F2
Medicare B1F5
Meredith, James B3F3
Middle East B3F5-B3F6
military B3F5
minimum wage B2F3
miniskirt B2F2 B3F4
Mississippi B1F1 B1F4 B2F3 B3F3
morality B3F2
Morse, Wayne B1F4
Moyers, Bill B2F4
Nader, Ralph B1F4
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People B1F5
National Students Association B3F2
NATO B1F2 B1F4
Nazism B2F2 B3F4
New York (State) B1F4-B1F5 B2F2-B2F3 B3F1-B3F4 B3F7-B3F8
New York City B1F4
New York Constitutional Convention B3F4 B3F6
New York Legislature B1F4 B3F2
New York lottery B3F8
Nickerson, Eugene B3F8
Nixon, Richard M. B3F4 B3F6
nuclear weapons B2F4
O'Connor, Frank D. B1F5 B2F3 B3F8
oil B3F6
Olympics B1F5
peace B1F5 B3F2 B3F4 B3F6 B3F8
police B1F5
politics B1F1 B1F5 B2F2-B2F3 B3F2 B3F4-B3F5
pollution B3F2 B3F4
poverty B1F1 B2F3
Powell, Adam Clayton B2F3-B3F4
Price, Cecil B1F4
prices B2F1
prisoners of war B1F5
public employees B3F2-B3F3
railroad industry B3F5
Reagan, Ronald B3F6 B3F8
religion B1F1 B1F3
Republican Party B2F3 B3F4 B3F8
Reuther, Walter B3F2
Rivers, L. Mendel B3F3
Rockefeller, Nelson B2F3 B3F1-B3F2 B3F4-B3F5 B3F8
Rockwell, George Lincoln B2F2
Romney, George W. B3F2 B3F4 B3F6 B3F8
Roosevelt Jr., Franklin D. B2F2-B2F3 B3F8
Rusk, Dean B1F3 B1F5 B3F2
Russell, Bertrand B3F5
Samuels, Howard J. B2F3 B3F8
segregation B1F5
Shaw, Clay B3F3
Sinyavsky Daniel case B1F2
Smith, Howard W. B1F5
socialism B1F2
South Africa B2F3
South America B3F4
Soviet Union B1F5 B2F4 B3F2 B3F5-B3F6
space exploration B1F4 B3F1 B3F4-B3F5
sports B1F5
Stalin, Svetlana B3F4
steel industry B2F1
stock market B2F2
strikes B1F5-B2F1 B3F1-B3F5
Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee B1F5
Suharto B1F4
Sukarno B1F4 B3F2
Supreme Court B3F6
Syria B3F1 B3F6
taxes B1F4 B2F3 B3F1-B3F2
teachers B3F5
Teamsters B3F2
Thant, U. B2F3-B2F4
The Beatles B2F2
The Death of a President B2F4
The Negro Family B2F3
Travia, Anthony J. B3F3-B3F4
Twiggy B3F3
U.S. Constitution B2F1
U.S. Flag B3F5
UFOs B1F2
unions B1F5-B2F1 B3F2-B3F3
United Nations B3F8
universities B1F4
Verwoerd, Hendrik Frensch B2F3
Vietnam War B1F2-B1F3 B1F5 B2F2-B2F4 B3F2-B3F6
violence B2F1 B3F2
voting B3F1 B3F3-B3F4
voting rights B2F3
war B2F3
Warsaw Pact B1F4
Westmoreland, William C. B3F4
Wilkins, Roy B1F5
Wilson, Harold B1F5 B3F5
Zedong, Mao B1F2-B1F3 B1F5-B3F1 B3F5-B3F6